<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[BLOG Progress Process]]></title>
  <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-25T12:12:18-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://ablwr.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ashley Blewer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Netflix for Books]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/09/25/netflix-for-books/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-25T12:01:14-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/09/25/netflix-for-books</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="images/oyster.png" alt="oyster" /></p>

<p>I came up with an idea to make a spoof/parody of the recently launched <a href="https://www.oysterbooks.com">Oyster</a>, a company that purports to be the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/08/07/technology/personaltech/aiming-to-be-the-netflix-of-books.html">“Netflix of books,”</a> allowing rentable access to digital books. This hit a sore spot among the librarians I know (and as a former librarian, I know many), because one of the biggest struggles in the field is increasing awareness in the capabilities of the modern library. Most libraries HAVE eBook access, plenty of it, and a lot of materials can be accessed through a library’s website without even having to go into the library. I think a service like Oyster has a lot of value, but I wanted to remind people that they can utilize the free resources available nearby.</p>

<p><img src="images/worldcat.png" alt="worldcat" /></p>

<p>So, I basically just made a splash page for WorldCat. WorldCat is a collective catalog used by over 72,000 libraries. Searching a book on WorldCat, a user can add their zip code and find the closest location of that resource, so she could know exactly where to go to pick it up. If I look up Harry Potter and request the eBook format, I can see that its available at several libraries near me, one of which is the Brooklyn Public Library. Assuming the user has a library card, she can just log in and get the book onto her preferred digital book reader in very little time. WorldCat is great, but its underused (just like our local libraries). It&rsquo;s also kinda ugly, so why not make it hip to modern internet eyes?</p>

<p><img src="images/netflixforbooks.png" alt="netflixforbooks" /></p>

<p>I really wanted to integrate the WorldCat API into this project, but unfortunately the API is not open and available to the public. This isn’t the time or place to ramble on about the benefits of open source and open access to databases and applications, but I would have been able to put a lot more time and effort into making a more beautiful and friendlier front-end for the face of public libraries. Alas, alas.</p>

<p>Let’s use libraries!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flatiron and Fog Creek Fellowship]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/09/18/flatiron-and-fog-creek-fellowship/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-18T11:21:07-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/09/18/flatiron-and-fog-creek-fellowship</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To follow up my last <a href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/09/18/breaking-it-down/">blog about blogging</a> (meta), here is the blog post I originally intended to write. I’m pushing it up the queue over the other 13 pending posts.</p>

<p>Flatiron School was hard. It was one of the toughest, enduring challenges I’ve ever done in my life, and also the most rewarding. I got completely comfortable working from 8am to 10pm every day, excited to write code and build stuff and make things happen. After graduation, it can be hard to not lose that momentum.</p>

<p>Before coming to Flatiron, I had a regular 9-5 job as cataloging manager at a film archive. On top of that, I did some freelance consulting work. Well, it was really more like sub-consulting, if that is a thing. Anyway, I worked a lot independently. I have a couple of friends that, for a while, paid for desks at a coworking space here in New York and it was hard for me to understand how someone could justify paying so much money for a desk while freelancing instead of just working from home (and thus having to work less because you don&rsquo;t have to work the extra amount it takes to pay for the coworking space desk). I could understand the social benefits of working around others, but overall I just never understood the &ldquo;going to a coffee shop to work&rdquo; thing. Throughout college, I always worked from my dorm or house and hardly set foot in the library except to grab up books (which is kinda funny, since I have an advanced degree in library and information science now). Back to the point: I started getting paid to work, which means I had to pay attention to what I was doing and work efficiently. With personal projects or homework, it&rsquo;s fine to dabble around. But when it&rsquo;s business, I knew I had to stay focused or I&rsquo;d have to start billing half-hours, which means I&rsquo;d work for 4 hours but only really work for 2, which is a waste of my own time because all 4 hours certainly still felt like I was working, even if half of it was non-billed procrastination time. I also have two cats. They are very cute, but they are also capable of being very annoying.</p>

<p>Anyway, this is how I discovered the joy of having a space dedicated to just working and I renounced all negative vibes I had towards paying $500 for a desk in Brooklyn. Back in South Carolina, I worked for a University on weekdays and spent my weekends working on projects at the University library. I&rsquo;d work from home on weeknights, but it was so much harder to get things done when I kept getting distracted by little things like dirty dishes, crooked books on a shelf, making tea, neighbors, or cats. Mostly the cats.</p>

<p>Getting back to the point&hellip; after Flatiron, we were welcome to continue working on campus, which is great! Fortunately for me and 15 other recently minted lady developers, I was selected to participate in the <a href="http://flatironschool.com/fogcreek">Flatiron / Fog Creek Fellowship</a>.</p>

<p>Here is what we all get, according to the website:</p>

<blockquote><p>What Fellows get:</p>

<p>• A dedicated mentor from both the Fog Creek and Trello teams</p>

<p>• Events with the Fog Creek and Trello staff including Cofounders Joel Spolsky and Michael Pryor</p>

<p>• A desk at Fog Creek</p>

<p>• Daily lunch</p>

<p>• Technical interview practice and guidance</p>

<p>• Four 1:1 pairing sessions</p>

<p>• Help choosing and feedback on a side project</p>

<p>• 1:1 lunch with your mentor every other week</p></blockquote>

<p>To summarize: A desk, a lunch, a dude telling you stuff. To be honest, I wasn&rsquo;t sure how this was going to go down at first. To be even more honest, I was a little sad to be separated from my Flatiron classmates that would still be working at the home base. But the baby bird has to leave the nest sometime&hellip; I was kinda excited about the desk, though. Because I knew being out of the Flatiron work-all-the-time mode was going to be hard, and not having a dedicated space to work was going to be even harder. Looking for a job is hard and I am just as busy now as I was when I was still in the program.</p>

<p>I missed the fellowship orientation because I was driving from South Carolina to New York with two desks to not-work-at-home-at and two cats, among other things, so I was a little nervous to just pop right into such a highly regarded software company.</p>

<p>Immediately, though, I was made to feel SO WELCOME. My mentor is SUPER RAD, he sent me a bunch of emails in advance, he read through my blog and had a lot of questions to ask me. He is always ready to sit down with me at any time to teach me some of the more theory-heavy aspects of computer programming that I mostly missed out on, to ask me about how my job search is going, or to just make me watch the first ten minutes of Up and explain how it relates to software engineering AND LIFE. Everyone at Fog Creek / Trello has been SOOOO extremely nice and welcoming, and I am so happy to be participating in the inaugural fellowship. The mentors all got together and came up with a dedicated time (and trello board) to helping all of us collectively train up on Computer Science fundamentals.</p>

<p>It truly feels like a fellowship, by the academic definition. We all get access to resources like desks and lunch and an unlimited snack bar (oh god, the snack bar, the snack bar&hellip;) and open access to a very nice espresso machine, but more importantly we get things like Joel Spolsky personally teaching us how to use the espresso machine (something that I think many established software engineers have dreamt about at night), casual lunch conversations about time travel (this comes up a lot), talent shows, board game nights, and Friday socials.</p>

<p>So&hellip; what&rsquo;s the lesson from this blog post? Desks are important for working hard, but more important than a desk and a space is the people that you surround yourself with when working, so I&rsquo;m thrilled to get to regularly hang with such a great team of people while I work on finding a place to work. Thank you so much, Flatiron and Fog Creek &amp; Trello!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Breaking it down]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/09/18/breaking-it-down/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-18T10:35:54-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/09/18/breaking-it-down</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I started at the Flatiron School in June, I told myself I was going to blog about my feelings and what I was learning every week. EVERY week. Then, when I graduated and inevitably had not written a single blog post about how it was going, I said I was gonna write a big ol’ jumbo blog post about the whole twelve weeks and everything I learned and how amazing it was.</p>

<p>Anyway, I graduated a month ago and there is still no e-novella.</p>

<p>This covers two important lessons in programming:</p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>Don’t get into code debt.</strong> If I had worked a little bit at a time towards my goal, I would have a weekly summary of what I was learning and doing while at Flatiron. But to speak to the other side of code debt: not writing about my experience was a bummer, but I was definitely spending it learning how to be a better programmer, which was the higher priority at the time, so I don’t feel too bad about it.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Break problems down into smaller problems.</strong> Since I wasn’t a diligent blogger, I wanted to just write one big post about Flatiron. But that’s such a large task! There’s SO much I want to cover, so where would I even begin? The most important advice I have to regularly give myself is to break problems down into smaller problems, otherwise I potentially get overwhelmed and not know where to start, which would result in just never starting.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Anyway, I hope to get those blog posts out in the world soon. If you are reading this because you are doing some cyber-research on the Flatiron School and are thinking of applying, do not hesitate for one second to get in touch! I love talking about it. I just haven&rsquo;t had the time to sit down and really blog it out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning (and trolling) with Popcorn.js]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/09/08/learning-and-trolling-with-popcorn-dot-js/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-08T11:01:02-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/09/08/learning-and-trolling-with-popcorn-dot-js</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Basically, I have a history of taking jokes too far. See also: <a href="http://instagram.com/p/ruP0rHjtbO/?modal=true">Tattoos of Avi’s face</a>. So when I was exploring <a href="https://www.mozilla.org/">Mozilla</a>’s <a href="http://popcornjs.org">Popcorn.js</a> and missing my Flatiron peers, I coded up a small app that would help me learn how to use Popcorn.js aaaaaaaand also troll my friends.</p>

<p>At Flatiron, we used a shared playlist system called <a href="http://sonos.com">Sonos</a>. Everyone could add tracks from online music collections like Spotify, Hype Machine, or Songza. Near the last third of the semester, as we were all on the brink of insanity and exhaustion, one song in particular kept making a rude appearance. I don’t know who started it or why, but the entire Flatiron office had to suffer through many, many, many instances of Seal’s Kiss from a Rose.</p>

<p>After Flatiron graduation, I was pretty excited to dig into some new projects while on the job hunt, but really missed hanging out with all of my Flatiron buds. To alleviate my withdrawl symptoms, I decided to integrate my Popcorn.js learning into an app to basically troll everyone I know.</p>

<p>To troll successfully, though, I first had to troll myself. Because music videos on youtube don&rsquo;t come with subtitles, I had to make those subtitles happen manually. I once had a job transcribing interviews, so I&rsquo;m pretty fast. But to get the timing right, I still had to submit myself to many, many listens of the same song.</p>

<p>Popcorn.js makes it easy to add supplemental media to video files based on timing.</p>

<p>Within a document listener, you create an instance variable with the .youtube suffix (obviously it&rsquo;s different if you are not using the YouTube API to access a video, but for this example, I used YouTube) and then declare a landing div ID and a link to the video itself.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'>   <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">pop</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">Popcorn</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">youtube</span><span class="p">(</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="s1">&#39;#video&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>     <span class="s1">&#39;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i4tTnIimi8E&#39;</span> <span class="p">);</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Afterwards, it&rsquo;s time to start adding footnotes! This takes in four options &mdash; a start time (in seconds), an end time (also in seconds, big surprise), the text you want to display, and the target div. The application of subtitle footnotes is simple, but it&rsquo;s easy to see what kind of complex and interesting things can be done based on video playback times.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'>   <span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">footnote</span><span class="p">({</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nx">start</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="mi">94</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nx">end</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="mi">97</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nx">text</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;Won&#39;t you tell me is that healthy, baby?&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nx">target</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;footnotediv&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="p">})</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p> At the end, just trigger play.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">pop</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">play</span><span class="p">();</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Try it yourself! <a href="http://ablwr.github.io/flatiron-karaoke">Sing your heart out here</a>.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s also an easter egg, but you have to patiently wait for it (or sing sing sing for it).</p>

<p>User feedback: It worked! Everyone typed in a song and got Seal back and tried it again because they thought it was a bug. NOPE. The only person that didn’t get trolled had preemptively trolled by searching for “Kiss from a Rose” so she didn’t know it was the only possible song that could be returned.</p>

<p>In the future, I’d like to spend more time trying to figure out how a real karaoke app could be created by automatically generating accurate subtitles. I’d also like to spend more time on the CSS styles so I could figure out how to fake the text highlighting on karaoke videos. As I mentioned earlier, there&rsquo;s an easter egg &mdash; I&rsquo;d like to work on incorporating more complex supplemental data alongside video files, such as Google maps, Wikipedia page load triggers, and images.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using videogrep to make supercuts]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/07/22/using-videogrep-to-make-supercuts/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-22T22:36:12-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/07/22/using-videogrep-to-make-supercuts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/antiboredom/videogrep">Videogrep</a> is a Python-based application that searches through a video file using its subtitles track and can cut video clips based on its search criteria.</p>

<p>Videogrep is SUPER easy to use&hellip; as long as ffmpeg is installed properly. If not, prepare for some configuring and installing.</p>

<p>I used videogrep to search through one of my favorite movies, Terrorvision, to find every time a character refers to something as &ldquo;The Pleasure (noun).&rdquo; Hint: it happens more times than you would think.</p>

<p>To do this, I only had to type one line and videogrep did the rest of the work.</p>

<p><code>python videogrep.py -i Terrorvision/Terrorvision.avi -o test_video.mp4 --search 'Pleasure'</code></p>

<p>It searched through the subtitles file and found six instances, which it printed to the screen along with their timestamps.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>524.357 to 527.86:  Pleasure Palace, here we come.
</span><span class='line'>1660.284 to 1663.453: Otherwise known as the Pleasure Zone.
</span><span class='line'>1734.4 to 1736.651: The Pleasure Den.
</span><span class='line'>1776.859 to 1779.527: on to the Pleasure Dome.
</span><span class='line'>1779.528 to 1782.905: To the Pleasure Dome.
</span><span class='line'>1840.756 to 1842.548: The Pleasure Dome.</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>If there is an error, at this point it will let you know. But if all goes well, the following will print to the screen:</p>

<p><code>Your video is ready ! Fingers crossed for the Oscars !</code></p>

<p>Here is the video supercut. Something that might have taken a few hours for me to piece together using my memory of the movie and video editing software was done in less than a minute using the powers of Python and FFMpeg.</p>

<p>Voila!</p>

<iframe src="//player.vimeo.com/video/99057389" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p> <p><a href="http://vimeo.com/99057389">Pleasure Supercut</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/orangelazarus">Ashley Blewer</a> on <a href="https://vimeo.com">Vimeo</a>.</p></p>

<p>This was just a simple example, but videogrep can get more specific based on the regular expression added into the search string. In the above example, I knew &ldquo;Pleasure&rdquo; was a proper noun because its the name of many rooms in the Putterman household. If I really wanted to grab every instance of the word, I would have had to search for &lsquo;pleasure|Pleasure&rsquo; to capture both uppercase and lowercase.</p>

<p>Videogrep can be even more powerful because it understands <a href="http://www.clips.ua.ac.be/pages/pattern-search">pattern recognition using pattern search</a>. I was able to extract what I wanted by just typing in one word, but it also understands word patterns. For example, you can use flags like JJ for adjective or NN for noun and it will extract every instance of a particular speech pattern.</p>

<p>It can also search for hypernyms, which are words that fit into a certain category and have a semantic relation to each other. For example, if you searched for automobile, you might also want to extract similar words like car, truck, or van. If you weren&rsquo;t picky about what kind of bird you were looking for, a hypernym search would result in crows, seagulls, and eagles.</p>

<p>Enjoy using videogrep and watch out for the monster!</p>

<iframe src="//player.vimeo.com/video/99093635" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p> <p><a href="http://vimeo.com/99093635">TerrorVision Monster</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/orangelazarus">Ashley Blewer</a> on <a href="https://vimeo.com">Vimeo</a>.</p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Canyon of Heroes]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/07/16/canyon-of-heroes/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-16T08:38:39-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/07/16/canyon-of-heroes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When walking to and from class every day at the bottom of Manhattan, I&rsquo;ve noticed plates of text on the ground with a date and name of a famous person. I didn&rsquo;t realize what these signs were about until I was walking out of the southmost Bowling Green stop and saw the initial plaque on the ground:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://ablwr.github.io/images/canyon-of-heroes.jpg" title="" ></p>

<p>After that, everything clicked! They are commemorating every ticker-tape parade held on Broadway, starting with the first to commemorate the dedication of the Statue of Liberty in 1886.</p>

<p>Before I came to the Flatiron School, I was working as a moving image archivist. I primarily worked with collections of newsreels from the 1920s and 1930s. My job was to catalog them and put them online for access. When I realized what the text on the ground stood for, I immediately ALSO realized that I recognized so many of the names because I had seen some of the actual parades happen (on film)! The text that struck me the most while walking up the street was this one:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://ablwr.github.io/images/canyon_of_heroes_amelia.jpg" title="" ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve <em>definitely</em> watched this footage. I ran to the (digital) archive and sure enough, <a href="http://mirc.sc.edu/islandora/object/usc%3A1866">there it was</a>.</p>

<p>Footage identification can be difficult when you don&rsquo;t have a lead, but this connection was pretty easy to make. I watched the footage, paying attention to the structures of the buildings, and then pulled up Flatiron School&rsquo;s address on <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/@40.705328,-74.013743,3a,75y,222.42h,90.24t/data=!3m4!1e1!3m2!1sxgNehf6c2LCLopGdOjKqkQ!2e0!6m1!1e1">Google Streetview</a>. Boom! It was a total match!</p>

<p>Here is a screencap of the Amelia Earheart ticker-tape parade superimposed on top of Google streetview.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://ablwr.github.io/images/broadway_thenandnow.png" title="" ></p>

<p>Pretty cool!</p>

<p>Bonus: The building that the Flatiron School is located in used to be the office building for the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_Star_Line">White Star Line</a>, which built the RMS Titanic (and many other, sturdier ships). Cool!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Form Helpers]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/07/15/form-helpers/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-15T22:38:07-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/07/15/form-helpers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Forms are hard! Forms are confusing in real life as well as on (or behind) the web. One problem with building web forms in Rails for me was that there are too many options! There are three distinct ways to create forms. And it’s also hard to tell which options are optional and which ones are required. Additionally, the syntax isn&rsquo;t always the same, so it can be hard to remember three different ways to do the same thing without mixing them up, especially as a beginner.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://ablwr.github.io/images/basic_form.png" title="" ></p>

<p>Here is the first form. This is the form that I think most people in my Ruby005 class would have written last week, before we learned about Rails form helpers. This is a form at its lowest level of abstraction while still being partially in Ruby, although it lacks Rails form helpers and form options helpers. This form just iterates through each ingredient and creates a checkbox. Checkboxes gives value of 1 if checked, 0 if not. And in the controller, we have to add ingredient_ids as an empty array in the params. It has to be called that or the whole thing won&rsquo;t work and all this code will be for naught.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://ablwr.github.io/images/form_tag.png" title="" ></p>

<p>Collection_check_boxes takes in five arguments, object, method, collection, value_method, text_method. Above, the recipe is the object, the ingredients_ids are the method, Ingredient.all is the collection, the :id is the value of the checkbox, and the name is the text to display with the checkbox. Best practice would be to abstract away the collection here so you are not calling a class in your View, and make a variable for Ingredient.all. Collection_check_boxes can look cumbersome with its five arguments, but its much cleaner than the previous code.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://ablwr.github.io/images/form_for.png" title="" ></p>

<p>In form_for, it looks like collection_check_boxes only takes FOUR arguments. And when you’re in formland, that’s an easy way to remember. Form_FOR takes FOUR. It actually takes five arguments, but one has already been declared at the beginning of the form. It’s @recipe.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s plenty more to learn about forms and form helpers, but I hope this little post can clear up some of the confusion surrounding usage.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[N+1+Arel+Me]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/07/15/n-plus-1-plus-arel-plus-me/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-15T21:56:54-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/07/15/n-plus-1-plus-arel-plus-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Component fails, the redundant N +1 configuration, the vulnerability of the system in the form provided. Part (s), one independent backup component at least. During normal operation, the active ingredients as the resistance standby backup system, or not to participate in the following way, passive / active. During failover, the drop in the system (the system availability, block) to restore transparency place during failover, but it depends on the particular solution.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://ablwr.github.io/images/arelenglish.JPG" title="" ></p>

<p>This activity &ndash; the other parts of the operation, the backup is a fully functional components, in one case, N 1 redundant, and can be active ingredients, but removed from component failure, the component will be able to run if the system is able to produce to be active.</p>

<p><i class='emoji scream'></i> <i class='emoji scream'></i> <i class='emoji scream'></i> <i class='emoji scream'></i> <i class='emoji scream'></i> <i class='emoji scream'></i> <i class='emoji scream'></i> <i class='emoji scream'></i> <i class='emoji scream'></i> <i class='emoji scream'></i> <i class='emoji scream'></i> <i class='emoji scream'></i> <i class='emoji scream'></i> <i class='emoji scream'></i></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Twitter bot roundup]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/07/01/twitter-bot-roundup/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-01T18:27:46-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/07/01/twitter-bot-roundup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><code>5.times { blog }</code></p>

<p>I wrote a few blog posts about the minor trials and tribulations of launching a Twitter bot that mimics a user&rsquo;s speaking patterns, based on a cool gem. Here they are, rounded up.</p>

<p><a href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/06/24/twitter-bots/">The Bots Are Coming! Twitter Bots!</a></p>

<p><a href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/06/25/twitter-bots-2-authorizing-the-bot/">Twitter Bots 2: Authorizing the Bot</a></p>

<p><a href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/06/28/twitter-bots-3-keeping-your-bot-alive/">Twitter Bots 3: Keeping Your Bot Alive</a></p>

<p><a href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/06/28/twitter-bots-4-mad-science/">Twitter Bots 4: MAD SCIENCE</a></p>

<p><a href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/06/29/twitter-bots-5-scheduling-tweets-with-cron/">Twitter Bots 5: Scheduling Tweets With Cron</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Twitter Bots 5: Scheduling tweets with Cron]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/06/29/twitter-bots-5-scheduling-tweets-with-cron/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-29T21:24:56-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/06/29/twitter-bots-5-scheduling-tweets-with-cron</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cron is a software utility that is used to schedule actions in time. It&rsquo;s great for handling reoccuring tasks. Twitter bots use a Cron statement to generate a tweet regularly. Cron tasks are super useful, but the syntax can be a little confusing and hard to remember.</p>

<p>The default bot tweets once a day, which is represented by <code>0 0 * * *</code></p>

<p>I changed my bot to tweet once an hour, which is represented by <code>0 * * * *</code></p>

<p>If I want my bot to tweet every hour from 9-5 on weekdays, it would look like <code>0 9-18 * * 1-5</code></p>

<p>Are you scratching your head? How can those numbers and letters mean anything?</p>

<p>In a row of five ( * * * * *), numbers break down like this:</p>

<ol>
<li> Minutes 2. Hours 3. Day (of month) 4. Months 5. Day (of week)</li>
</ol>


<p>That makes sense. Sort of. Except for having two different ways to represent time in a day, especially when they are not next to each other! Day of the month can be any number between 1-31 and is contingent on the month field. Day of the week is any number 0-6 and represents Sunday-Saturday.</p>

<p>The astericks means &ldquo;every.&rdquo; If a field has an astericks, it will trigger the event at that time interval.</p>

<p>Expressions aren&rsquo;t limited to asterisks and numbers. Other special characters include the slash (<code>/</code>), the comma (<code>,</code>), and the hyphen (<code>-</code>). The slash is used for increments of ranges. If I wanted to schedule an event to occur every five hours, I would use the string <code>0 */5 * * *</code>. Commas are used to separate items in a list. If I wanted an event to occur five minutes past the hour and five minutes before the hour, I could use the expression <code>5,55 * * * *</code>. Hyphens denote ranges. If I wanted to schedule an event to occur at the top of every hour during the Monday-Friday workweek, I would write <code>0 0 * * 1-5</code>.</p>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t want to figure out all of this syntax and just want to stay a die-hard Rubyist, you can also just install the gem &ldquo;whenever&rdquo; (<a href="https://github.com/javan/whenever">available here</a>). Another way to integrate Cron syntax into Ruby apps is the gem <a href="https://github.com/jmettraux/rufus-scheduler">Rufus-scheduler</a>.</p>

<p>Important note: If you are updating your bot&rsquo;s Cron settings, you have to re-run the archive and modeling files to see reflected updates.</p>

<hr />

<p>More info:</p>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cron">Cron on Wikipedia</a></p>

<p><a href="http://railscasts.com/episodes/164-cron-in-ruby">RailsCasts #164 Cron in Ruby</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Twitter Bots 4: MAD SCIENCE]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/06/28/twitter-bots-4-mad-science/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-28T21:09:57-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/06/28/twitter-bots-4-mad-science</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My twitter bot was born on the same day as my BFF (bot-ferverent friend) Athena&rsquo;s bot. In fact, we live together and were both working on our bots on the same night in different places because I was still at Flatiron and she was at home, and we didn&rsquo;t realize until our bots were nearly launched that we had both been working on the same project (and probably could have finished more quickly, as I was having trouble with something she had solved and she was having trouble with something I had solved). Pair programming is important! Anyway&hellip; since we are both bot-obsessed and I like data experiments as well as science experiments, I asked Athena for her bot&rsquo;s model file, which is json-formatted data of all of her tweets. I plugged her json data into a file with all of my json data and merged them together using the &ldquo;ebooks consume&rdquo; data-mixer that comes with the twitter_ebooks gem. Shortly after that, I had spawned a new daughter-bot, <a href="https://twitter.com/ashthena_ebooks">@ashthena_ebooks</a>, which is a combination of both of our tweets. Right now, this bot is a little biased towards my tweets, since I have a lot more than she did, but I hope to condense and mix that data up a bit more in the future, to produce weirder results.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p>Much like the smell of vinegar syndrome in the morning.</p>&mdash; ɐuǝɥʇɥs∀ (@ashthena_ebooks) <a href="https://twitter.com/ashthena_ebooks/statuses/483414614978613248">June 30, 2014</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Twitter Bots 3: Keeping your bot alive]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/06/28/twitter-bots-3-keeping-your-bot-alive/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-28T20:31:52-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/06/28/twitter-bots-3-keeping-your-bot-alive</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-partner="tweetdeck"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/wetted_ashes">@wetted_ashes</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/ablwr">@ablwr</a> Just spent too much time coding and having so many excellent things to read thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/timezones?src=hash">#timezones</a></p>&mdash; ¡ɹǝʍǝlq ʎǝlɥs∀ (@ablwr_ebooks) <a href="https://twitter.com/ablwr_ebooks/statuses/478713633023602688">June 17, 2014</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>Once a Twitter bot has been configured, it has to stay running in order to stay alive. And for that, it needs a server. When I was debugging my bot, I was running it off of my computer and got notifications of activity in my terminal. This works if I want my bot to only be active when I am active, but I want my bot to be available all day and night!</p>

<p>The most logical way to do that would be to deploy my bot&rsquo;s code to a Heroku instance. It&rsquo;s free and super easy, especially if you already have a good grasp on git workflows. Basically you just have to&hellip;</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>git init
</span><span class='line'>git add .
</span><span class='line'>git commit -m "BOTS"</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>then,</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>heroku create
</span><span class='line'>git push heroku master</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>That&rsquo;s it! That is it. Actually, that is not it, because I had to log onto the heroku web interface and adjust the Dynos worker to 1 instead of 0.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://ablwr.github.io/images/herokurunner.png" width="800" title="'heroku page'" ></p>

<p> But after that, my bot was again operational and back to her normal (myself)
self.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-partner="tweetdeck"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/ablwr">@ablwr</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/trlwagner">@trlwagner</a> The pass is lurking in the reboot, everyone get renewed at 21, and I do not like that.</p>&mdash; ¡ɹǝʍǝlq ʎǝlɥs∀ (@ablwr_ebooks) <a href="https://twitter.com/ablwr_ebooks/statuses/478715343737602049">June 17, 2014</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Twitter Bots 2: Authorizing the Bot]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/06/25/twitter-bots-2-authorizing-the-bot/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-25T12:54:34-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/06/25/twitter-bots-2-authorizing-the-bot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For me, the hardest part of getting a Twitter bot up and running was negotiating with Twitter&rsquo;s API keys and application settings. The primary reason for this was probably that I kept getting overly excited and jumping ahead, trying to finish the project too soon. I first set up an app by registering my primary twitter account. Turns out that wasn&rsquo;t necessary at all, and I could access and download my tweets just by using <a href="https://github.com/marcel/twurl">twurl</a> to collect authenticate and grab my main account&rsquo;s twitter archive. I THINK. Those authentication details went into a hidden file, .ebooksrc, in my computer&rsquo;s main user directory. I know because I had to break into it several times and switch out the keys in order to get it to work, but most users shouldn&rsquo;t need to open it again, once it&rsquo;s in there.</p>

<p>To get the bot operational, I had to create an dev account and app using my bot&rsquo;s twitter account (oh yeah, I also had to register a new twitter account &mdash; but that&rsquo;s obvious, right? I&rsquo;m not talking to a bot, I&rsquo;m talking to a human&hellip; right?)</p>

<p>Under My Applications (next to my user profile), I created a new app. Under the API Keys tab, I generated some access tokens. The consumer and OAuth details can then be added to the bot&rsquo;s bots.rb file, along with the bot&rsquo;s username and the bot model (in my case, my main twitter account).</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>CONSUMER_KEY = ""
</span><span class='line'>CONSUMER_SECRET = ""</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>




<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>  Ebooks::Bot.new("") do |bot| # Ebooks account username
</span><span class='line'>  bot.oauth_token = "" # oauth token for ebooks account
</span><span class='line'>  bot.oauth_token_secret = "" # oauth secret for ebooks account
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  make_bot(bot, "") # This should be the name of the text model generated from the base twitter account
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Sounds easy, but I had such a hard time! Writing it all up, I am embarassed that it took me so many tries to get it right. My problem was that I first thought that the CONSUMER_KEY fields needed to come from my main twitter account instead of from the bot&rsquo;s account. Then, I changed the CONSUMER_KEY details but also changed the info in the .ebooksrc file. Then, I changed them both around again but didn&rsquo;t refresh my OAuth token.</p>

<p>The final step was that my bot was running but unable to do anything because the API Keys permission access level was set to read-only. It is not super-clear in the documentation, but the account generating the access token has to have a valid phone number associated with it in order to get granted permission for read/write/execute status. After confirming with a phone number, my bot was able to talk to people and generate its own tweets based on my model.</p>

<p>A final important debugging note: After changing the permission access level from read-only to read/write, you will probably have to regenerate the API keys and add the new codes to the app.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The bots are coming! Twitter bots!]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/06/24/twitter-bots/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-24T23:10:17-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/06/24/twitter-bots</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I accepted a spot in the Flatiron School Ruby005 class, I knew my social life and, uh, casual internet-browsing life (?) would be cut dramatically down while I would be focusing all of my efforts on learning Ruby. I didn&rsquo;t want my friends to miss me too much (which is hard, since I also had to move from South Carolina to New York), so I decided to build a twitter bot that could tweet and talk to my friends.</p>

<p>Fortunately, there&rsquo;s already a Ruby gem that does all of the work for me. So I didn&rsquo;t really have to build a bot, I could just launch one! I used the gem found <a href="https://github.com/mispy/twitter_ebooks">here</a> and pulled in the example bot&rsquo;s code. When I got stuck, I referenced <a href="https://github.com/ScaryEnderman/Twitter-Bots-Tutorial">this bot tutorial</a>. Setting up the bot and modifying the code was easy, but I hit a few snags trying to cooperate with the Twitter app API and OAuth.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s how the twitter_ebooks gem works.</p>

<ol>
<li>The gem pulls in your twitter history in json format.</li>
<li>Then, it parses through the json data and identifies words and phrases according to grammatical structure.</li>
<li>It randomly generates sentences based on a user&rsquo;s tweet history. A cron job is set up to tweet randomly once a day, but I bumped that up to once an hour.</li>
<li>It knows how to respond to other users when they tweet at the bot.</li>
<li>It has a keyword list and will favorite or retweet tweets in its timeline that use those keywords.</li>
</ol>


<p>Here are a few examples of what my bot has to say:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p>CSS is in this instance, or is, at minimum, I&#39;ll take 6.</p>&mdash; ¡ɹǝʍǝlq ʎǝlɥs∀ (@ablwr_ebooks) <a href="https://twitter.com/ablwr_ebooks/statuses/481632877323354112">June 25, 2014</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>




<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p>&#8230;Damn it, iPhone, I hate it when you get a job at a grocery store.</p>&mdash; ¡ɹǝʍǝlq ʎǝlɥs∀ (@ablwr_ebooks) <a href="https://twitter.com/ablwr_ebooks/statuses/480258821844377600">June 21, 2014</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>




<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p>Tumblr adding fake film grain, tulips, u-matic tape players, cleaning my ears with a q-tip, maps&#8230;</p>&mdash; ¡ɹǝʍǝlq ʎǝlɥs∀ (@ablwr_ebooks) <a href="https://twitter.com/ablwr_ebooks/statuses/479307552946421762">June 18, 2014</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>But the best part of having a Twitter bot is that it can interact with other users! Classmate <a href="http://randallreedjr.com/">Randall</a> asked her for some advice:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/ablwr_ebooks">@ablwr_ebooks</a> What should I do this weekend?</p>&mdash; Randall Reed Jr. (@randallocalypse) <a href="https://twitter.com/randallocalypse/statuses/480034237391704064">June 20, 2014</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-partner="tweetdeck"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/randallocalypse">@randallocalypse</a> I hope this suggests a return of the insane hotels.</p>&mdash; ¡ɹǝʍǝlq ʎǝlɥs∀ (@ablwr_ebooks) <a href="https://twitter.com/ablwr_ebooks/statuses/480034319030026240">June 20, 2014</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>That&rsquo;s my bot! Have your bot add my bot at <a href="http://www.twitter.com/ablwr_ebooks">@ablwr_ebooks</a>. Stay tuned for some more technical blog posts about working through the Twitter authentication steps, understanding CRON, modifying a bot, deploying to heroku, and ~mad science experiments~.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Regular Expression Options]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/06/16/regular-expression-options/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-16T18:26:07-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/06/16/regular-expression-options</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When working with Regular Expressions, I mostly ignored these optional suffixes because I didn&rsquo;t want to further complicate an already complicated aspect of programming. But since there are only four options, I decided to take a break from other complications and break down what each regex suffix can do.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>i</strong></p>

<p>i stands for <strong>INSENSITIVE</strong>! But not like that jerk that cut in front of you when changing trains at Union Square this morning. It means that it is case insensitive! You can save some keystrokes and be more precise by using i to eliminate or swap a word for a paragraph.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>m</strong></p>

<p>The next option is the letter m. M stands for <strong>MULTILINE MODE</strong>! Mmmm! What does that mean? Rubular sums it up succinctly as &ldquo;make dot match newlines.&rdquo; Still lost? The m option helps the dot (also known as a period or a full stop) character, which represents any character in a regex, match everything INCLUDING the invisible new line character. The new line character is represented in a regex or in programming as \n. If you are worried that your new line might mess up your regex, the m option can help mesh all lines together.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>o</strong></p>

<p>Next up is the letter o. O stands for <strong>ONCE</strong>! ONE TIME, ONE CHANCE, ONE SHOT! To substitute once. Substitute once means that any #{&hellip;} substitutions that occur in a regex can only occur one time and then they are OUT!</p></li>
<li><p><strong>x</strong></p>

<p>Finally, the letter x. X stands for&hellip; <strong>Xtended</strong> mode! Also known as Extended Mode. Regular expressions can be really complicated, so the x at the end allows for extra room in the expression such as spaces, new lines, and comments. Then, the regex is more readable and less scary. Another tip: to comment in a regex, use ?#. But if you use ?#, you also have to use x.</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coding guide for newbs]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/05/22/coding-guide-for-newbs/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-22T23:03:45-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/05/22/coding-guide-for-newbs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Everyone who has been around me regularly for the past (???) amount of time knows that I&rsquo;ve been all about learning to code as much as possible, and I&rsquo;ve been roping a few of my friends into doing the same. So, a question that I get a lot is &ldquo;Where do I begin?&rdquo; There are plenty of good guides on the internet, but I wanted to write up my own guide, particularly targeted to archivists and librarians coming out of library and information science programs. I think programming basics should be a mandatory component of ALA-accredited programs, but I&rsquo;ve found that at least in my MLIS experience (and anecdotally from many others), there is a severe lack, even in basic technical knowledge of computers.</p>

<p>Please note that I am a novice speaking to people that are even greener than me, but here are some of the web resources I recommend for figuring out if you <em>even like programming</em> and want to consider diving deeper, like I have. This is basically an extended form of an email I would otherwise be writing to my friend Marleigh.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to first talk about some more general, theoretical strategies and then go into a guide of some of the learning resources I&rsquo;ve used and recommend.</p>

<p><strong>Generally</strong></p>

<p>The following resources I am going to mention are great and learning how to program has never, ever been easier than now, with a nearly endless supply of videos, podcasts, blog posts, MOOCs, books, and Stack Overflow answers. But the most important thing to realize that if you want to learn how to code, you are gonna have to do a lot of coding and problem-solving all by yourself. The best way to learn things is to try to make them, fail, and try again. That being said, sometimes it&rsquo;s good to just get your feet wet before diving right in.</p>

<p>The second big thing is thinking about what you want to learn. If you are an absolute newbie and have never used the less-than or greater-than sign for anything other than emoticons, I recommend working on HTML/CSS first. Some people might argue that they are not technically programming languages, but it really doesn&rsquo;t matter and that is a stupid argument. After that, I recommend a few others: JavaScript, Python, and Ruby. All-in-all though, don&rsquo;t sweat too hard over which language to pick, because you are working on just learning the fundamentals, which are similar across all programming languages.</p>

<p>Ruby: I deliberated between Python and Ruby for a long time, but eventually settled on Ruby. They are both extremely popular &ldquo;first language&rdquo; choices because they are easy to use and learn, and they are very similar. If you are just trying to get a feel for what you like, it really doesn&rsquo;t matter which one you choose. My reasons for choosing Ruby are personal. 1. As a moving image archivist, I see a lot of work needing to be done with access to digital content, and a lot of that work is done in Ruby. So it is favored by my community. 2. The Ruby community strives to be very welcoming and open, and seeks to increase diversity. 3. A lot of the coding bootcamps I was looking at were Ruby-based, so that made my decision easier (as I now will be attending Flatiron School). 4. I&rsquo;m interested in web development, particularly with video on the web, and I feel like the Ruby/Rails framework suits my interests there.</p>

<p>Python: I started off learning Python, because that&rsquo;s what Codecademy teaches in its Code Year track. I loved it, I still love it, and I like how elegant it looks just based on the &ldquo;meaningful white space&rdquo; component of the language. I really think Python is probably the &ldquo;best&rdquo; first language to learn because of its &ldquo;zen&rdquo;-like methodology that pushes for code to be clean, concise, well-written, but most of all, easy to read and understand by all. If you intend to work in academia or on the science side of things, Python is a definite winner here. For general automation work in your personal life, Python is great. If you are interested in hardware hacking or think you might be, Python is also great.</p>

<p>JavaScript: If you are digging HTML/CSS and like web development stuff, JavaScript is a good language to pick. The web is sorta being taken over by JavaScript and JS libraries. If you are into design, knowing more about JavaScript will only help you in the future.</p>

<p>When learning, it&rsquo;s good to generally stay away from Rails (Ruby), Django (Python), and JQuery (Javascript) and try to focus on learning the actual language itself, not just the frameworks. The fundamentals are important. Even if things are harder, you are learning more by doing it &ldquo;the hard way.&rdquo; At least, that&rsquo;s what I tell myself. Don&rsquo;t avoid these things like the plague, I just recommend focusing on the basics of programming.</p>

<p><em>Flatiron School and Makersquare pre-work</em></p>

<p>Both of these coding bootcamps require 100-150 hours of pre-work from their students before the start of their classes. Fortunately for the rest of us, their learning materials are free and available online, so they can be used as guides for people just starting out.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://www.edx.org/course/harvardx/harvardx-cs50x-introduction-computer-1022">CS50x</a></strong></p>

<p>I took this at-your-own-pace online MOOC based on Harvard&rsquo;s CS50 intro to computer science course when I started my graduate program, a bit over two years ago. I hands-down recommend it to anyone that wants a strong starting foundation in computer science, and I think it really sets someone&rsquo;s mind up for a better understanding of programming language syntax and structure. I pretty much just watched all of the lectures and didn&rsquo;t do the homework, but I still feel like I got a lot out of the class. If a class like this had been taught in my first semester as an undergraduate, it would have changed my life completely.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.codecademy.com">Codecademy</a></strong></p>

<p>In conjunction with CS50 lectures, I worked through the Code Year track on Codecademy, which doesn&rsquo;t seem to be (easily) available anymore. Anyway, Codecademy is maybe the most popular &ldquo;learn to code&rdquo; resource, and for good reasons. (One of the reasons being that it&rsquo;s free, so there&rsquo;s a very low barrier to entry). If you are absolutely brand new to programming, I recommend churning through the entire HTML/CSS track (or projects, as they seem to be now). It may be familiar, it&rsquo;s easy to understand, and even if you absolutely hate programming and never want to do it again for the rest of your life, you will at least know how to link to a website without using an enriched web editor.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://teamtreehouse.com">Treehouse</a></strong></p>

<p>After hitting up a full track of resources on Codecademy, or even before, I recommend Team Treehouse. Their teaching style is through videos followed by quizzes (either questions or coding exercies), which I find to be a nice, relaxing way to learn or refresh skills when I want to still feel productive but not work too hard.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.codeschool.com">Code School</a></strong></p>

<p>Code School is great! But definitely much more challenging than Treehouse, which is why I recommend cruising through Treehouse first. Once you are feeling like a coding whiz  styling up a few websites on Treehouse, Code School is there to firmly put you back into your incredibly novice place. Code School looks easier than Treehouse, but some of the training wheels are off. Even with things I felt comfortable with, like CSS or MySQL, I would sometimes have to review the materials several times before I could solve the code exercises.</p>

<p><strong>Just Doing It</strong></p>

<p>I mentioned this earlier, but I really want to drive home this point. The above resources are great for getting your feet wet, but the only real way to really learn something is to just do it yourself, and frequently. You can do a million web exercises and read a redwood tree&rsquo;s worth of books and bootstrap up to your neck, but it&rsquo;s not gonna stick until you&rsquo;ve spent a few hours really trying to tackle a problem. The above materials are training wheels, and the sooner you take them off and try to ride/write, the better. If you get unstuckably stuck, you can always put them back on, or try a smaller/easier project. The main thing is to try, try, try. You will fail a thousand times, but keep trying.</p>

<p><strong>Other stuff</strong></p>

<p>There are so many other online resources and essential guides, <a href="http://www.openculture.com/freeonlinecourses">MOOCs</a>, but I just wanted to highlight a few. Maybe I will do a follow-up post with some other resources that I consider to be super-duper-helpful or essential to my learning. In the meantime, enjoy these and don&rsquo;t hesitate to get in touch with any questions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[May 8th and decision-making.]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/05/12/may-8th-and-decision-making/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-12T13:09:35-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/05/12/may-8th-and-decision-making</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is gonna be super-cheesy. I wrote this on May 8th, which is an important day for me.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m getting ready to do something kinda crazy. I&rsquo;m quitting my pretty-swell job, moving across the country, packing up my stuff, leaving many of my wonderful friends, finding extended cat-sitters for my two cats, and plopping down some serious cash. For a 3-month immersive web development course in New York. Of course, there are some obvious perks: I love New York and want to live there again, I also have wonderful friends in the city, the tech field is booming with well-paying jobs, and it&rsquo;s an interesting and creative field. This final one being the most important to me and I&rsquo;ll try to address it in another &ldquo;talking about feelings&rdquo; post.</p>

<p>Regardless, it&rsquo;s a big jump. And I can&rsquo;t help but think about another big jump that I made exactly one decade ago(!). It&rsquo;s so hard to believe that ten years have passed, but here it goes. When I was a teenager, I saved up all of the money I made working (side note: it&rsquo;s way easier to save money when you don&rsquo;t have to pay rent+utilities). I saved up all my money and put it towards a 3-month immersive Japanese language course in Tokyo. SO EXCITING, getting to learn a new language (which I later minored in), living in a new country (still my favorite place in the world), experiencing so many new things. On Saturday, May 8, 2004, me and two suitcases got on a plane to Tokyo and off I went and it&rsquo;s probably one of the best decisions I&rsquo;ve made in my life.</p>

<p>As I was making this decision about going to a coding bootcamp, all of these memories kept coming back to me. I thought a lot about how important that time in Tokyo was, how much it meant to me, and how much I learned. My Japanese isn&rsquo;t anywhere near fluent these days, but I still have an extremely strong foundation in the language that I am confident would come back if I spent a few weeks immersed back into it. I thought about all the things I learned, the people I met, everything I saw, all the hours I spent wandering around Tokyo by myself, the museums I went to, the host family I have a life-long connection with, and an endless amount of other things, big and small. Matsuri, konbini, chikatetsu, tsuyu. When I think back on how much those 3 months affected me and made me grow as a person, it became nearly impossible for me to decline to make a similar decision ten years later.</p>

<p>Because of all of this, I have been thinking a lot about the kind of person I was ten years ago and the kind of person I am now. And thinking about the kind of person that I will be in another ten years (37? Ahhhhh!). The kind of person I WANT to be in ten years, and where I want to be in ten years. I even looked back at my old LiveJournal, which was a little bit horrifying and it was hard to recognize myself, but there I am. I&rsquo;ve been thinking a lot about the potential path that I am currently on and the potential path if I take this leap of faith, and I only see an expanded potential for learning and growth as a person, which is just what I am looking for in life. I have a lot of feelings about this, but will curb them for now (for here).</p>

<p>So, as I post this new blog post at the start of a new adventure, cheers to May 8, cheers to giant leaps of faith, and cheers to always growing and learning.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blogging for hackers.]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/05/11/blogging-for-hackers/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-11T15:35:15-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/05/11/blogging-for-hackers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello. I am starting this blog specifically to talk about my upcoming dive into web development. I have been doing &ldquo;programmery stuff&rdquo; for a while (a few months, a few years, 15 years, depends on your definition) but I start at the Flatiron School in 3 weeks for their Ruby 005 Cohort and am seriously jumping in. From some intense googling, I am under the impression that we may have to keep a technical blog, so I figured I&rsquo;d go ahead and get one started now, even if it&rsquo;s not a requirement.</p>

<p>Like a good hacker newbie, I diligently checked out Octopress, which defines itself as &ldquo;a blogging framework for hackers.&rdquo; It&rsquo;s based on Jekyll, integrates easily with Github Pages, and overall seemed like the right choice for what I will be doing since it requires a little more know-how than a one-click Wordpress install.</p>

<p>And no joke! It was a workout. I&rsquo;m at novice-comfortable level with Ruby/Rails, Git, and the command line and have never used Sass/SCSS, Haml, or Markdown. But I expected to install it in twenty minutes and feel like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://37.media.tumblr.com/67251c0e29d86a669149105bf1abf00b/tumblr_msxaxuidVy1shab7zo1_500.gif" alt="Hacking the planet" /></p>

<p>But ended up spending over an hour and a truly embarrassing number of commits (I just checked &mdash; 52 total!) and feeling more like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://i.kinja-img.com/gawker-media/image/upload/s--PZD0YHjX--/hgcxrafqyfevwmtsngsq.gif" alt="Hacking cough" /></p>

<p>I got it working enough to do this and modify the theme a little bit, but barely. I haven&rsquo;t sorted out the problem of having to run &lsquo;bundle exec&rsquo; in front of every rake command or figured out why I have two different folders for this blog, but I&rsquo;m at least dedicated to figuring that out. And figuring out many more future problems publicly, here. I&rsquo;m a pretty private person when it comes to most things, but am forcing myself to be okay with being very publicly &ldquo;dumb&rdquo; when it comes to programming and web development. The tech field needs a lot of things, but something it really needs is the death of the &ldquo;elitist hacker&rdquo; mentality, and the rise of collaboration, empathy, and knowing that it&rsquo;s okay to not know something.</p>

<p>Still, I&rsquo;m looking forward to going from hammering out problems like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://files.gamebanana.com/img/ico/sprays/mario_hammer.gif" alt="Mario hammer" /></p>

<p>To hammering them out like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://fireden.net/4chan/images.4chan.org//vg/src/1362844057459.gif" alt="Hammer time" /></p>

<p>Wish me luck! Either personally or below when I get a chance to figure out how to turn comments on. It&rsquo;s gonna be a long journey.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IS THIS THING ON?]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/05/09/is-this-thing-on/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-09T12:34:01-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/05/09/is-this-thing-on</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the most sincere &ldquo;HELLO? WORLD???&rdquo; I have ever made.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
