<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: video | BLOG Progress Process]]></title>
  <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/categories/video/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-11T09:59:45-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://ablwr.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ashley Blewer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning (and trolling) with Popcorn.js]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/09/08/learning-and-trolling-with-popcorn-dot-js/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-08T11:01:02-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/09/08/learning-and-trolling-with-popcorn-dot-js</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Basically, I have a history of taking jokes too far. See also: <a href="http://instagram.com/p/ruP0rHjtbO/?modal=true">Tattoos of Avi’s face</a>. So when I was exploring <a href="https://www.mozilla.org/">Mozilla</a>’s <a href="http://popcornjs.org">Popcorn.js</a> and missing my Flatiron peers, I coded up a small app that would help me learn how to use Popcorn.js aaaaaaaand also troll my friends.</p>

<p>At Flatiron, we used a shared playlist system called <a href="http://sonos.com">Sonos</a>. Everyone could add tracks from online music collections like Spotify, Hype Machine, or Songza. Near the last third of the semester, as we were all on the brink of insanity and exhaustion, one song in particular kept making a rude appearance. I don’t know who started it or why, but the entire Flatiron office had to suffer through many, many, many instances of Seal’s Kiss from a Rose.</p>

<p>After Flatiron graduation, I was pretty excited to dig into some new projects while on the job hunt, but really missed hanging out with all of my Flatiron buds. To alleviate my withdrawl symptoms, I decided to integrate my Popcorn.js learning into an app to basically troll everyone I know.</p>

<p>To troll successfully, though, I first had to troll myself. Because music videos on youtube don&rsquo;t come with subtitles, I had to make those subtitles happen manually. I once had a job transcribing interviews, so I&rsquo;m pretty fast. But to get the timing right, I still had to submit myself to many, many listens of the same song.</p>

<p>Popcorn.js makes it easy to add supplemental media to video files based on timing.</p>

<p>Within a document listener, you create an instance variable with the .youtube suffix (obviously it&rsquo;s different if you are not using the YouTube API to access a video, but for this example, I used YouTube) and then declare a landing div ID and a link to the video itself.</p>

<p>```javascript</p>

<p>   var pop = Popcorn.youtube(</p>

<pre><code> '#video',
 'https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i4tTnIimi8E' );
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Afterwards, it&rsquo;s time to start adding footnotes! This takes in four options &mdash; a start time (in seconds), an end time (also in seconds, big surprise), the text you want to display, and the target div. The application of subtitle footnotes is simple, but it&rsquo;s easy to see what kind of complex and interesting things can be done based on video playback times.</p>

<p>```javascript</p>

<p>   .footnote({</p>

<pre><code>  start: 94,
  end: 97,
  text: "Won't you tell me is that healthy, baby?",
  target: "footnotediv"
</code></pre>

<p>   })</p>

<p>```</p>

<p> At the end, just trigger play.</p>

<p>```javascript</p>

<pre><code>pop.play();
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Try it yourself! <a href="http://ablwr.github.io/flatiron-karaoke">Sing your heart out here</a>.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s also an easter egg, but you have to patiently wait for it (or sing sing sing for it).</p>

<p>User feedback: It worked! Everyone typed in a song and got Seal back and tried it again because they thought it was a bug. NOPE. The only person that didn’t get trolled had preemptively trolled by searching for “Kiss from a Rose” so she didn’t know it was the only possible song that could be returned.</p>

<p>In the future, I’d like to spend more time trying to figure out how a real karaoke app could be created by automatically generating accurate subtitles. I’d also like to spend more time on the CSS styles so I could figure out how to fake the text highlighting on karaoke videos. As I mentioned earlier, there&rsquo;s an easter egg &mdash; I&rsquo;d like to work on incorporating more complex supplemental data alongside video files, such as Google maps, Wikipedia page load triggers, and images.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using videogrep to make supercuts]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/07/22/using-videogrep-to-make-supercuts/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-22T22:36:12-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/07/22/using-videogrep-to-make-supercuts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/antiboredom/videogrep">Videogrep</a> is a Python-based application that searches through a video file using its subtitles track and can cut video clips based on its search criteria.</p>

<p>Videogrep is SUPER easy to use&hellip; as long as ffmpeg is installed properly. If not, prepare for some configuring and installing.</p>

<p>I used videogrep to search through one of my favorite movies, Terrorvision, to find every time a character refers to something as &ldquo;The Pleasure (noun).&rdquo; Hint: it happens more times than you would think.</p>

<p>To do this, I only had to type one line and videogrep did the rest of the work.</p>

<p><code>python videogrep.py -i Terrorvision/Terrorvision.avi -o test_video.mp4 --search 'Pleasure'</code></p>

<p>It searched through the subtitles file and found six instances, which it printed to the screen along with their timestamps.</p>

<p><code>
524.357 to 527.86:  Pleasure Palace, here we come.
1660.284 to 1663.453: Otherwise known as the Pleasure Zone.
1734.4 to 1736.651: The Pleasure Den.
1776.859 to 1779.527: on to the Pleasure Dome.
1779.528 to 1782.905: To the Pleasure Dome.
1840.756 to 1842.548: The Pleasure Dome.
</code>
If there is an error, at this point it will let you know. But if all goes well, the following will print to the screen:</p>

<p><code>Your video is ready ! Fingers crossed for the Oscars !</code></p>

<p>Here is the video supercut. Something that might have taken a few hours for me to piece together using my memory of the movie and video editing software was done in less than a minute using the powers of Python and FFMpeg.</p>

<p>Voila!</p>

<iframe src="//player.vimeo.com/video/99057389" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p> <p><a href="http://vimeo.com/99057389">Pleasure Supercut</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/orangelazarus">Ashley Blewer</a> on <a href="https://vimeo.com">Vimeo</a>.</p></p>

<p>This was just a simple example, but videogrep can get more specific based on the regular expression added into the search string. In the above example, I knew &ldquo;Pleasure&rdquo; was a proper noun because its the name of many rooms in the Putterman household. If I really wanted to grab every instance of the word, I would have had to search for &lsquo;pleasure|Pleasure&rsquo; to capture both uppercase and lowercase.</p>

<p>Videogrep can be even more powerful because it understands <a href="http://www.clips.ua.ac.be/pages/pattern-search">pattern recognition using pattern search</a>. I was able to extract what I wanted by just typing in one word, but it also understands word patterns. For example, you can use flags like JJ for adjective or NN for noun and it will extract every instance of a particular speech pattern.</p>

<p>It can also search for hypernyms, which are words that fit into a certain category and have a semantic relation to each other. For example, if you searched for automobile, you might also want to extract similar words like car, truck, or van. If you weren&rsquo;t picky about what kind of bird you were looking for, a hypernym search would result in crows, seagulls, and eagles.</p>

<p>Enjoy using videogrep and watch out for the monster!</p>

<iframe src="//player.vimeo.com/video/99093635" width="500" height="282" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p> <p><a href="http://vimeo.com/99093635">TerrorVision Monster</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/orangelazarus">Ashley Blewer</a> on <a href="https://vimeo.com">Vimeo</a>.</p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
