<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: personal | BLOG Progress Process]]></title>
  <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-25T13:31:13-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://ablwr.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ashley Blewer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Breaking it down]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/09/18/breaking-it-down/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-18T10:35:54-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/09/18/breaking-it-down</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I started at the Flatiron School in June, I told myself I was going to blog about my feelings and what I was learning every week. EVERY week. Then, when I graduated and inevitably had not written a single blog post about how it was going, I said I was gonna write a big ol’ jumbo blog post about the whole twelve weeks and everything I learned and how amazing it was.</p>

<p>Anyway, I graduated a month ago and there is still no e-novella.</p>

<p>This covers two important lessons in programming:</p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>Don’t get into code debt.</strong> If I had worked a little bit at a time towards my goal, I would have a weekly summary of what I was learning and doing while at Flatiron. But to speak to the other side of code debt: not writing about my experience was a bummer, but I was definitely spending it learning how to be a better programmer, which was the higher priority at the time, so I don’t feel too bad about it.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Break problems down into smaller problems.</strong> Since I wasn’t a diligent blogger, I wanted to just write one big post about Flatiron. But that’s such a large task! There’s SO much I want to cover, so where would I even begin? The most important advice I have to regularly give myself is to break problems down into smaller problems, otherwise I potentially get overwhelmed and not know where to start, which would result in just never starting.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Anyway, I hope to get those blog posts out in the world soon. If you are reading this because you are doing some cyber-research on the Flatiron School and are thinking of applying, do not hesitate for one second to get in touch! I love talking about it. I just haven&rsquo;t had the time to sit down and really blog it out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
