<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: me, | BLOG Progress Process]]></title>
  <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/categories/me/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-24T22:15:12-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://ablwr.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ashley Blewer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2016 new years resolutions]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2016/01/02/2016-new-years-resolutions/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-02T12:04:58-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2016/01/02/2016-new-years-resolutions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/coolstorybro.png" title="" ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not trying to act like I don&rsquo;t care about git commit logs and streaks, because I do. In a greedy, childish way, I do and I will continue to stare deep into the soft green blocks of a Github streak. I even sit briefly-moody knowing that a job change in this year removed so many little boxes from the front half of this graph.</p>

<p>Blogging your resolutions and goals is a good way to put yourself to task. <a href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/12/27/new-years-resolutions/">Last year</a> I viciously wanted to do more (and I did). This year, I want to do less (but I probably won’t).</p>

<p>But my motto for this year is “Do a few things well.” (It&rsquo;s also &ldquo;no new projects&rdquo; and you&rsquo;ll see why later.)</p>

<p> &hellip;</p>

<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned data-instgrm-version="6" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:658px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:8px;"> <div style=" background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50.0% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;"> <div style=" background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAAGFBMVEUiIiI9PT0eHh4gIB4hIBkcHBwcHBwcHBydr+JQAAAACHRSTlMABA4YHyQsM5jtaMwAAADfSURBVDjL7ZVBEgMhCAQBAf//42xcNbpAqakcM0ftUmFAAIBE81IqBJdS3lS6zs3bIpB9WED3YYXFPmHRfT8sgyrCP1x8uEUxLMzNWElFOYCV6mHWWwMzdPEKHlhLw7NWJqkHc4uIZphavDzA2JPzUDsBZziNae2S6owH8xPmX8G7zzgKEOPUoYHvGz1TBCxMkd3kwNVbU0gKHkx+iZILf77IofhrY1nYFnB/lQPb79drWOyJVa/DAvg9B/rLB4cC+Nqgdz/TvBbBnr6GBReqn/nRmDgaQEej7WhonozjF+Y2I/fZou/qAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;"></div></div> <p style=" margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/6iqUd-Sco3/" style=" color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;" target="_blank">Had to painfully convince myself not to invent a new typeface in the making of this, which just emphasizes my need to heed this advice.</a></p> <p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;">A photo posted by 🐱Ashley🐱Blewer🐱 (@ablwr) on <time style=" font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;" datetime="2015-08-18T22:31:51+00:00">Aug 18, 2015 at 3:31pm PDT</time></p></div></blockquote>


<script async defer src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script>


<p>&hellip;?</p>

<p>Last year, it made sense to be so dedicated to the hustle because I was struggling to get somewhere. At the start of this year, I am here — I am where I want to be, and I just need to remind myself that it’s okay to take a breath if I need to before continuing climbing up the mountain. That it&rsquo;s okay to say no, sorry, I do not have time for that. It&rsquo;s okay to not submit to speak at conferences. That it&rsquo;s okay to spend a full Saturday doing nothing but clicking the &lsquo;next&rsquo; button on Netflix if that is what I need to recover from a stressful week. I think this is something most people do without an anvil of guilt hovering above them, but I guess I am not most people.</p>

<p>Also, making time for friends is always, always worth it. I have felt especially grateful this year to know so many comprehensively wonderful people, so many that I can&rsquo;t even count.</p>

<p>BUT. How can I put this&hellip;</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Have a productive weekend.</p>&mdash; Shit Academics Say (@AcademicsSay) <a href="https://twitter.com/AcademicsSay/status/667847591850283009">November 20, 2015</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>Must my determination of success always be contingent on productivity levels, even through weekends and holidays? <em>I&rsquo;m not even an academic!</em></p>

<p>I don’t <em>really</em> want to (nor plan on) being less busy, but I have two problems: I care a lot and I care about a lot of things. And what I have lacked is an opportunity to focus more on fewer things and do them well. Design has been on my mind lately—- I&rsquo;m not a bad designer (nor is it necessarily a truth that I am good, but I&rsquo;ve had enough training and practice to side-eye inconsistent page-centering practices, et al), but all the design work I’ve done is pretty bad because it is done as an afterthought to solving another problem and I don&rsquo;t give myself the time to do it well.</p>

<p>For some of this year, I was working as a &lsquo;front-end developer&rsquo; on a project but ended up spending the majority of my time setting up site backups, wrangling database structures, and designing the site. Labels don&rsquo;t matter that much to me, but at a point I became very aware that if my work was the be judged as a &lsquo;front-end designer&rsquo;, it wouldn&rsquo;t make me feel very good considering only 1/6th of my time (of which was already limited &mdash; as nonprofit budgets are, no shame there) had been dedicated to that component. So by the time I got around to writing HTML/CSS/JS, you bet I popped Bootstrap on it and you might even find some !importants strewn throughout a hastily-gathered base CSS template (sorry my front-end pals if you&rsquo;ve since left screaming &mdash; the site is not done, I will make the !important un-important in due time, but sorry about the decidedly un-hip Bootstrap). When this site goes live or the code is made open, will I seem bad or lazy? I <em>like</em> to think that I am neither, but the constraint of time would perceive me as such. This also goes along with me <em>liking to think</em> that I have a &ldquo;strong attention to detail.&rdquo; Doesn&rsquo;t everybody like to think that about themselves? But when there are a million details instead of a thousand details, it&rsquo;s harder to give them all attention.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not close to burning out (maybe because I just basically spent the last two days Straight Chillin'), but recognizing burnout as a thing and taking preventative measures is important in this upcoming year. A problem for me is that I <em>like</em> doing it all but there is so much value in focusing on less in order to produce better results.</p>

<p>For context, here’s an abbreviated list of things I will fret over in 2016: <a href="https://nypl.org">New York Public Library</a> (in many ways, in many applications, and most important of all), <a href="https://mediaarea.net/MediaConch/">MediaConch</a>, <a href="https://xfrcollective.wordpress.com/">XFR Collective</a>, <a href="https://github.com/bavc/qctools">QC Tools</a>, <a href="http://amiaopensource.github.io/ffmprovisr/">ffmprovisr</a>, <a href="http://www.screenslate.com/">Screen Slate</a>, <a href="http://lamama.org/">La MaMa</a>, Actual Material, Code4lib’s video stream, AMIA committees, W*iHPEM formations… and I’m sure there’s more than one of that-other-thing-I’ve-already-forgotten-about and that-thing-I-don’t-yet-know-about. There are also other, small, secret things that are just for me and I am sad they are not given the care and attention I wish I had for them. When I see an amazing side project or personal portfolio site, my eyes always flash green for a second, envious of time. I also tend to add things to that pile &mdash; the personal-projects-pile &mdash; because it is so much easier and more fun to think of something I&rsquo;d like to do rather than actually spend time doing it. So a side-goal is to not start anything new until I&rsquo;ve finished what has been started.</p>

<p>But&hellip; right? That&rsquo;s a lot of stuff. Keep me in check. Keep me in ample quantities of chocolate-covered espresso beans. 2016 is going to be great but only if we take care of ourselves and of each other.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
