<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: quitting your job | BLOG Progress Process]]></title>
  <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/categories/quitting-your-job/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-10T00:37:19-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://ablwr.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ashley Blewer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Historical post: Leaving my job]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/05/08/historical-post-leaving-my-job/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-08T22:44:33-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/05/08/historical-post-leaving-my-job</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Leaving any job is hard. Leaving a job you really love is even harder. Someone asked me when I was turning in my notice if quitting was as cathartic as it should feel, and I said I felt like I was getting a divorce. Y'know. &ldquo;I love you, but this just isn&rsquo;t working.&rdquo;</p>

<p>My job is great. However, it is also stagnant. I found myself frequently on auto-pilot, even though a lot of my work is compelling, complex, and ever-changing. I love working with newsreel outtakes from the 1910s-1940s and there&rsquo;s a constant change in material. I love working with students because there&rsquo;s always a new question about cataloging that I hadn&rsquo;t thought about. All in all, it&rsquo;s pretty good. However, it also isn&rsquo;t going anywhere and isn&rsquo;t going to lead to a more permanent position. Resources are slim, and I had to configure an eclectic, cumbersome workflow because I was not allowed to have a computer fast enough to view video files (a key component to the job).</p>

<p>In addition to feeling stagnant, there are some severe ethical concerns in any mid-tier state University&rsquo;s hiring practices, but particularly the one I have been working for, that affects my department very directly. I could complain for days about this and related issues, but it doesn&rsquo;t make for polite blogging, so I will digress.</p>

<p>I mention it because I am concerned about my field. I&rsquo;m less concerned about my specific field (moving image archiving) but very much concerned about the larger field of archives. While obsessively researching my decision to leave, I emailed a former archivist that also did a coding bootcamp, asking basically if I was unhappy in my situation because it was specific to my location, or if it was representative of the field as a whole. I tweeted something to the tune of &ldquo;I need to know that the place I work at is not representative of the field I work in.&rdquo; Unfortunately, her response as someone in the field longer than I have been is that my experience and fears of joblessness, jumping from grant-funded position to the next, and intense bureaucratic issues seemed very much in line with those of most others in the archival field, and that scares me.</p>

<p>Moving image archiving, preservation, and access to these materials are things I care about SO MUCH. However, I am faced with the reality that in order for me to have other things that I want in life (living wage, job security, job flexibility, retirement fund, adequate health care, vacations), I have to come to terms with the fact that I might have to consider doing something else, at least for a little while. At the very least, I am also very passionate about &ldquo;computery stuff&rdquo; and programming skills and the &ldquo;world wide web,&rdquo; (oh boy don&rsquo;t get me started on the free and open web), and feel that I can really make a more tangible difference in general (world) and in specific (archive&rsquo;s wacky website) if I work up some deeper programming knowledge and skills. (I could mope forever about how I wish I had done that ten years ago, but I&rsquo;ll save that rant-o-thon and put my efforts into educating young women in computer science instead).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
