<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: history | BLOG Progress Process]]></title>
  <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/categories/history/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-28T14:49:05-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://ablwr.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ashley Blewer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Canyon of Heroes]]></title>
    <link href="http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/07/16/canyon-of-heroes/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-16T08:38:39-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ablwr.github.io/blog/2014/07/16/canyon-of-heroes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When walking to and from class every day at the bottom of Manhattan, I&rsquo;ve noticed plates of text on the ground with a date and name of a famous person. I didn&rsquo;t realize what these signs were about until I was walking out of the southmost Bowling Green stop and saw the initial plaque on the ground:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/canyon-of-heroes.jpg" title="" ></p>

<p>After that, everything clicked! They are commemorating every ticker-tape parade held on Broadway, starting with the first to commemorate the dedication of the Statue of Liberty in 1886.</p>

<p>Before I came to the Flatiron School, I was working as a moving image archivist. I primarily worked with collections of newsreels from the 1920s and 1930s. My job was to catalog them and put them online for access. When I realized what the text on the ground stood for, I immediately ALSO realized that I recognized so many of the names because I had seen some of the actual parades happen (on film)! The text that struck me the most while walking up the street was this one:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/canyon_of_heroes_amelia.jpg" title="" ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve <em>definitely</em> watched this footage. I ran to the (digital) archive and sure enough, <a href="http://mirc.sc.edu/islandora/object/usc%3A1866">there it was</a>.</p>

<p>Footage identification can be difficult when you don&rsquo;t have a lead, but this connection was pretty easy to make. I watched the footage, paying attention to the structures of the buildings, and then pulled up Flatiron School&rsquo;s address on <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/@40.705328,-74.013743,3a,75y,222.42h,90.24t/data=!3m4!1e1!3m2!1sxgNehf6c2LCLopGdOjKqkQ!2e0!6m1!1e1">Google Streetview</a>. Boom! It was a total match!</p>

<p>Here is a screencap of the Amelia Earheart ticker-tape parade superimposed on top of Google streetview.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/broadway_thenandnow.png" title="" ></p>

<p>Pretty cool!</p>

<p>Bonus: The building that the Flatiron School is located in used to be the office building for the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_Star_Line">White Star Line</a>, which built the RMS Titanic (and many other, sturdier ships). Cool!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
